Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1800-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- New-York Historical Society: construction of Central Park West building, and views of the 2nd Avenue building before the move, 1903-1908 (Offsite-box 18, Volume 165)
  Ground breaking and cornerstone laying; sequential views as the building goes up; views of the 2nd Avenue building, including exterior and interior views showing galleries, offices, library, including view showing materials in crates.
- New and old New York: [album of photographs of New York used for lectures by F.B. Kelley], [1900-1920] (Offsite-box 18, Volume 166)
  Obituary of F. B. Kelley (1934) pasted on inside of front cover, along with note identifying the photographs as those used by Kelley for lectures; Catalogue of photographs laid in; Haight bookplate; early N.Y. in paintings and engravings; Fraunces Tavern; statues of Washington, Ericsson, Lafayette; Trinity Church and churchyard; street architecture details such as an old pump, mill stones used as paving, mile stones, etc.; government buildings, taverns; Brooklyn and Williamsburg Bridges, including a construction view; harbor views; fire houses; old houses; the tombs; demolition of reservoir; Astor place, Cooper Square; cemeteries; block houses; N-YHS building, 2nd Ave.; memorials and plaques; historic trees; Castle Clinton.
- West Point Class of 1861 (Offsite-box 18, Volume 167)
  Portraits of cadets and teachers.
- [Albums of photographs of fire-fighting Vol. 1], 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 168.1)
  Horse-drawn fire-engines racing to fires, including engines 74, 56, Engine 76 at a fire; views of fire-fighters on the scene, including: Manhattan Soap Co. fire, W. 36th Street, April 10, 1911; a lumber yard and laundry, 52nd street near 10th Ave., June 17, 1911; Equitable Building fire scene, showing it becoming increasingly covered in ice, and firemen and officials also ice-coated; Tenement fire on W. 47th, January 13, 1912; some reproduced in Smyth Fire albums.
- [Albums of photographs of fire-fighting Vol. 2], 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 168.2)
  Unidentified warehouse fire scene, with Engine Co. 8; Chrystie Street, Feb. 12, 1912, depicting ice-coated tenements, and Dep. Chief Langford; men of Engine 13; firemen taking hoses up the stairs and into a brownstone style house; 56 Vesey Street fire, Feb. 13, 1912; Engine 74, Truck 25 Battalion Chief Grey in a carriage; Truck 16 on W. 24th Street, Oct. 19, 1912; Truck 58 taking up their hoses; fire scene, 383 Amsterdam Ave., Lieut. Murphy and Short.
- Photographs [Snapshots of unidentified family and friends, and western views], [1899] (Offsite-box 19, Volume 169)
  Views on a small farm, probably used as a vacation home, including women on a horse, in a wheelbarrow, relaxing on the porch, swimming, groups working and posing with farm tools, women wearing sunbonnets, children, women playing tennis, and a drawing of the farm house showing its cupola and garrets by F[rank] Pember; western views including rock formations [Garden of the Gods?], people on horse back including Indians, soldiers and sailors marching.
- Photographic Album: Members of Assembly of the State of New York, for 1881. (Offsite-box 19, Volume 170)
- [Album of cartes de visites of Civil War generals and admirals], undated (Offsite-box 19, Volume 171)
- Album of photographs of the School of Mines, Columbia University, 1878 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 172)
  Shows professors and students at the school, each identified; photographers include Alman & Co. and Rockwood; includes three Japanese students.
- New York / published by A. Wittemann, souvenir books and post cards, Brooklyn, N.Y., [printed by] The Albertype Co., Brooklyn, N.Y., [1930-1939] (Offsite-box 20, Volume 173.1)
- New York / published by A. Wittemann, souvenir books and post cards, Brooklyn, N.Y., [printed by] The Albertype Co., Brooklyn, N.Y., [1930-1939] (Offsite-box 20, Volume 173.2)
  Various paging showing New York city scenes including lower Manhattan, parks, streets, statues, rivers, hotels, Easter Sunday on Fifth Avenue, public buildings including the New York Public Library, City Hall, Grand Central Station.
- [Greenwich Village street scenes], [1950-1959] (Offsite-box 20, Volume 174)
  Greenwich Village: store fronts, restaurants, coffee houses, lunch counters, specialty shops, pawn shops and shop signs, groceries, a cat asleep among plumbing (?) supplies, stoops and doorways, signs.
- Catskill Water System / Commissioner Charles N. Chadwick, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 175.1)
  Ca. 100 photos of Catskill Water System including views of the Hudson River, portraits of officials, reservoirs, tunnels under construction, and restoration of reservoir sites; includes African American workers.
- Catskill Water System / Commissioner Charles N. Chadwick, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 175.2)
  Site of Ashokan reservoir before construction; dams under construction, Esopus Creek, Camp City, including homes, school, hospital, other camps; Hudson River, drilling rigs, roads.
- [Album of photographs of Morristown, N.J.], [1900-1929] (Offsite-box 46, Volume 176)
  Civic and historic buildings, parks, monuments, homes and businesses, Theodore Roosevelt at a whistle-stop in Morristown; a flood; various portraits laid in; also includes clippings; most views from the 1920s, many taken for A.H. Pierson by Charles Curtis, with earlier and possibly later views interspersed in the album.
- [Ferryboat album Vol. 1], [1860-1949] (Offsite-box 177.1)
- [Ferryboat album Vol. 2], [1860-1949] (Offsite-box 177.2)
  Green, Norvin H., compiler. Embossed on cover: "U.S. Army Air Forces, Aerial Photographic Section." Primarily views of New York harbor ferries: including original photographs, including a stereograph, copy photographs from various New York institutions, including New York Public Library, the Museum of the City of New York, Mariners' Museum and other institutions, clippings from 19th and 20th century publications showing ferries, ferry accidents, a Civil War scene showing troops landing from steamboats, schedules, an invitation to ride "The Narrows" on its innaugural voyage in 1946, ferry passes for various companies, interiors and engines, ferry terminals, including lower Manhattan, Brooklyn and Astoria, copies of prints and paintings, copies of currency with a ferry pictured on it, views of New York Harbor, and Manhattan streets.
- House of Irving McHesson, 234 E. 68th St., New York, [1960-1979] (Offsite-box 21, Volume 178)
  Color photographs of interior of McHesson home, documenting furniture and portraits, some of which were given to the "Historical Museum"; letter enclosed with the album describes the views, and gives genealogical information about the sitters in the portraits.
- The Marine Museum of the City of New York, [1940-1949] (Offsite-box 21, Volume 179)
  Interior views of the museum showing figureheads, ships' models, copies of painting and prints, a barometer, silver punch bowl, galleries and a docent giving a talk to a group of young men.
- [Album of photographs of trip in Europe], [1910] (Offsite-box 22, Volume 180)
  Views in Europe: women playing shuffleboard on deck and other ship-board views; gardens, buildings, homes; people in small early automobile; [Lake Como?]; local residents, woman and boy with baskets on their backs; soldier; a gardener; sheep; villas; views in Italy including Venice and Rome; street scenes including local people; horse omnibus outside Hotel Londres; white-washed coastal town built on steep slopes.
- [Brooks family album], 1893-1904 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 181)
  Title based on images of the people aboard the Lasca, a yacht which was owned by J.E. Brooks in 1893 when the photos were made; other subjects include groups in St. Agathe, Canada, views aboard the cruiser "Olympia"; a large house in White Plains; group outfitted for ride in touring car; other views in Canada, including street scenes, a waterfall (Montmorency?), views at the Montreal Hunt Club, and West Hatley; on board the Lasca at Bar Harbor, 1904; street scene in Rockport, Mass.; beach scenes.
- [Album of portraits, most from Pennsylvania], [1870-1909] (Offsite-box 22, Volume 182)
  Cabinet cards, cartes-de-visite and tintypes; men, women and children, including man in Masonic regalia, group portraits and child with Easter basket and stuffed bunny; copy of pictorial Lord's Prayer.
- [Albums depicting harbor defenses Vol. 1] / E.V.W. Keen, Naval Net Depot, New York, Feb. 10, 1942, 1941, Oct.-1942, Jan. (Offsite-box 22, Volume 183.1)
  Anti-Motor boat boom, 3-B, fixed obstructions, October 2, 1941 to November 14, 1941 and --at the entrance to New York Harbor, November 22, 1941 to January 3, 1942: process of rigging and laying fixed obstructions (baulks).
  2 vols. each with two parts
- [Albums depicting harbor defenses Vol. 2] / E.V.W. Keen, Naval Net Depot, New York, Feb. 10, 1942 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 183.2)
  Anti-Submarine net of 4-foot mesh at the entrance to New York Harbor, started January 10, 1942; construction and laying of net.
- Photographs 122 St., College Point, 1940 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 184)
  Map showing 122nd Street in College Point with annotations showing where photographs were made. Photographs are mounted on pages that are accordion-hinged so that they can be opened to one long view; views of homes, the business district, including a movie theater, automobiles, advertisements.
- Photographs, William St. Subway: B.W. Greenlaw, 1915-1917 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 185)
  Spero, Charles, photographer. Album documenting the construction of the William Street Subway in lower Manhattan, by Smith, Hauser and MacIsaac, Inc. contractors, 1915-1917; views in the tunnels showing men at work drilling piles, etc.; buildings in the area, including no. 122, oldest standing bldg. on William Street, Pine, Pearl Sts. and Hanover Sq.; man welding; contractor's truck; overhead gas bypass pipe; wooden water main and valve removed during the construction; views depicting the underpinning work done on the building along the route; cross section drawing of the tunnel; concrete mixer; Fulton, Wall and William, showing network of pipes below the street.
- West Indies, 1912 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 186)
  Postcard of the "Victoria Luise" of the Hambug-Amerika line and other ships and locations; photographs by Albert Eugene Gallatin of Cuba, including the Maine, Morro Castle and child in Mardi Gras costume in Havana; scenery in Puerto Rico, including touring car on dirt road, building and homes; Jamaica: scenery, including car, seashore and small thatched house; Panama: postcards of the canal, photos of locks; Venezuela: views in Caracas including soldier, women on street, George Washington statue, man on burro; Trinidad: La Brea asphalt lake, black boy with monkey and parrot, police, "coolies" from India; Barbados: black market women in Bridgetown, and street scenes; Martinique: small boats in the harbor of Fort de France, statue of Josephine, street in St. Pierre; St. Thomas: harbor, children, general view; photograph by Wm. Nielson of other people on the cruise, including women dancing on deck of boat, group on horseback; photos by Miss Madelin Knowlton of groups visiting sugar mill, markets, three girls looking out window, residents of Trinidad, Barbados; 8x10 of woman in a garden laid in.
- New York Division, Mexican Border Service, 1916 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 187)
  Album documenting New York Division on the border during the punitive expedition against Pancho Villa, including the 1st New York Cavalry and its captain, William J. Donovan (later General); army unit in [New Mexico? Texas?] soldiers in cars, trucks, in front of tents, soldiers drilling, cavalry parades; barracks, cook shacks, tents, interior view of office; officers with pelican; houses and buildings in surrounding area; a river; horsedrawn ambulances; includes one portrait that is probably of Gen. John J. Pershing.
- [Keteltas family album], [1860-1879] (Offsite-box 23, Volume 188)
  Cartes-de-visite of Keteltas, Hunt, Moulton, Renard, Dion, Withers, Stuyvesant, Belmont, Johnson, Hoffman, Tighe, Gentil, Leary, Wright, Fitzgerald, Kingsland, Rathbone, Crosby, Harris, Hutton, and other families, and a group portrait of soldiers, and a tintype of a group out of doors.
- Hommage a la mission citoyens Americains qui ont visite la France du 3 au 10 Mai 1918 / Section Photographique de l'Armie Francaise. (Offsite-box 24, Volume 189.1)
  Group portraits of French and American dignitaries; views of groups visiting Versailles, Reims, Verdun and other battlefields, and group wearing gas masks, and visiting air fields with airplanes arrayed in formation; people pictured include Joffre, Niox, Ambassador Sharp of the U.S., Loucher and Payeur, Gen. Hirschauer; soldiers on horseback passing through village at the front.
- Hommage a la mission citoyens Americains qui ont visite la France du 3 au 10 Mai 1918 / Section Photographique de l'Armie Francaise. (Offsite-box 24, Volume 189.2)
  Les Americains en France, including soldiers relaxing in camp, drilling with weapons, American aviators with planes; French tanks and artillery; Verdun, general views and ruins; Reims: ruins, including the cathedral; destruction in Nancy; views of munitions factories in France.
- [Warner Family album], [1870-1889] (Offsite-box 24, Volume 190)
  Cartes-de-visite and cabinet card portraits of Warner, Herrick, Howland, Whittemore, Humbert, Opdyke, Lee, Taylor, Wallis, and other families. See also Album #191.
- [Herrick Family album], [1870-1889] (Offsite-box 24, Volume 191)
  Cartes-de-visite and cabinet card portraits of Herrick and Howard families, and unidentified persons. See also #190.
- Photographs of Men, [1869-1870] (Offsite-box 25, Volume 192)
  Portraits of governor, lt. governor and others, possibly other politicians.
- Portraits of relatives, notables and professional associates of Tom Thumb ... from the collection of his widow, the Countess Magri, [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 25, Volume 193)
- Our Home [Ludington Home], 1911 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 194)
  Album created by Mrs. Benjamin Ludington for her daughter Helen Ludington Powers; portraits of Mr. and Mrs. Ludington; interior views of the home at 44 69th Street East showing woodwork, ornate furnishings and knick-knacks and art work, as well as more informal rooms including bed and dressing room, library and informal sitting room; man in office; portrait of the family. See also Album #135.
- [Album of views collected and arranged by Albert T. Weston], [1900-1920] (Offsite-box 25, Volume 195)
  " Views of New York City, 1648 to 1848 and 1911---1912": small early lithographs, probably from Valentine's manual, or similar publication, showing historic buildings and sites; "Brooklyn Houses of Colonial Days"; same places in photographic postcards; views in Hawaii in September, 1920, by Weston (who was an U.S. Navy surgeon), including palm trees, Diamond Head, beaches, gardens, government buildings, hotels, homes, hula dancers and musicians; "H.R.H. on his visit to Honolulu, Official and Unofficial, other views of H.R.H. in other lands"; "Mount Rainier, including a view of Narada Falls by Prof. J.B. Flett, December 8th, 1920; postcards of Florida, including St. Augustine, Daytona, Orlando and other locations; postcards of California, Quebec and Paris.
- [Photographs: the William Nicholls Family], [1940-1959] (Offsite-box 26, Volume 196)
  Snapshots and photographic greeting cards showing the Nicholls Family and friends and relatives; includes children with pets, and toys, playing the piano and at the beach.
- Leonard F. Beckwith [Album of Consolidated Telegraph and Electrical Subway Company construction photographs], [1889] (Offsite-box 26, Volume 197)
  Beckwith was an engineer with Consolidated Telegraph and Electrical Subway Construction; each photographs captioned in letterpress on the mount; Pach Bros. photographs; construction photos depicting the placement underground of telegraph and electrical lines, with surroundings sometimes visible, including views on 6th Avenue, Madison Avenue; Broadway; Greene Street; 14th Street; 53rd Street; includes workers.
- Album of photographs of Madison Square Gardens (McKim, Mead & White) before and during demolition, [1925] (Offsite-box 46, Volume 198)
  Primarily views of the second Madison Square Garden which was designed by McKim Mead and White showing interiors, including performance area set up for a circus, with a swimming pool; men boxing in MacLevy Gym; looking down at a stage; the box office area, stairways; exterior views: the roof garden during the demolition of the structure; views from Madison Square Park; advertisements for Ringling Bros. Circus and MacLevy's gym; views showing the tower, including the archer sculpture and including the surrounding area; building decked out in bunting; arcade walkway out front; also includes copies of earlier photographs, including copies of the Central Railroad freight station, later the first Madison Square garden, and including view of building as Barnum's Hippodrome; includes views by Brown Bros. and Wurts Brothers.
- [Cabinet card album of prominent New Yorkers], [1870-1889] (Offsite-box 26, Volume 199)
  Photographs and prints depicting Thurlow Weed, Thomas Armitage, Andrew Mills, Horace F. Clark, Geo. T. Trinble, John A. Kennedy, Chester Car[?], David Babcock, Queen Victoria (not in album); Com. Vanderbilt 2d, Nathaniel Haywood, Em. L. Ehlers, Capt. Frederick Wagner, Gov. Morgan, Geo. H. Andrews, Chas. Folger, Howard Crosby, Edw. Haight, Leonard Hazeltine, Webster Wagner (poem dedicated to him laid in), David Banks, Aras G. Williams, Chauncey M. Depew, Tom C. Acton, Horace H. Day, William H. Vanderbilt, Joel Ehrlach, Smith Ely, Thos. Boese.
- The Lake Champlain Tercentenary Celebration, July Fourth to Ninth, Nineteen Hundred and Nine, 1909 (Offsite-box 26, Volume 200)
  Invitation, guest cards, transportation tickets for Champlain celebration and Hudson Fulton Celebration pasted inside front cover; views of the lake, copies of engravings of Champlain, his battle with the Iroquois and Benedict Arnold's ship the Royal Savage, Thomas MacDonough, Ethan Allen, ruins of Fort Ticonderoga, and the restoration of the fort; copy of painting of battle of Cumberland Bay; replica of Champlain's caravel, recovery of the hull of Arnold's schooner, ruins of Ft. Ticonderoga, Mrs. H.P. Pell, at whose direction old Fort Ticonderoga is being restored; montage of portraits of Lake Champlain Tercentenary commissions of New York and Vermont; Gov. Hughes and commission members at Plattsburgh; the Pavilion, or old Pell Homestead, during restoration; commission members by automobile; courthouse and other views at Plattsburgh, including parades; the yacht Valcour; Gov. and Mrs. Hughes arriving; residence of Hon. Walter C. Witherbee, Port Henry; the torpedo boat Manly; ruins of Ft. Amherst; throng leaving the steamer at Crown Point Forts; sketch of the floating island used for the presentation of the Indian pageants, and photos of the pageant; Hugh's delivering address at Crown Point Forts; Seth Low, President Taft, his daughter Helen, Col. Robert M. Thompson, Elihu Root, other speakers; Gov. Hughes and Admiral Uriu of Japan; Taft and family aboard houseboat Sliouan; group portraits on the steps of the Pell Homestead; Hotel Champlain (with article about fire there); Religious exercises at Isle Le Motte, Vt.; Soldiers and Sailors Monument on Crab Island; drawing of Champlain Monument, and article regarding it; some photographs and articles laid in; some photographs by Beals, L.E. Shattuck, George T. Woodward, Trumbull.
- [Album of photographs of Boston and vicinity], 1857-1890 (Offsite-box 27, Volume 201)
  Views of the Back Bay at different times; street views; State houses; hotels; homes; churches. See album #202.
- [Album of photographs of New York City, 1870-1890], [1870-1899] (Offsite-box 47, Volume 202)
  American Studio photographs of streets in New York including Broadway between Bowling Green and 42nd street, Wall Street, Park Row, Fifth Avenue; New York Harbor, ships under sail and at dock; men on tower of Brooklyn Bridge; some views are copies from earlier works by Anthony and others, including one labeled as from a daguerreotype from 1853. See also album #201.
- Mobilization and review, Atlantic Fleet, Oct. 25th -Nov. 2nd, 1911 (Volume 203)
  Views of ships in New York Harbor, and New York waterfront; rowboats and launches tending the ships, views on board, showing artillery, ships moored to one another. See also album #204.
- Hudson-Fulton Celebration, Autumn, 1909 (Offsite-box 27, Volume 204)
  Postage stamp on inside of front cover commemorates event; views of ships, New York Harbor, the Statue of Liberty, ferries and steamboats, submarines, battleships and other navy vessels, the S.S. Robert Fulton, the S.S. Lusitania at the Cunard dock, tall ships and naval vessels from other countries, replica of the Half Moon, parade views. See also album #203.
- Hudson Fulton Celebration, September 25th - Oct. 9, 1909 (Offsite-box 72, Volume 205)
  Spooner and Wells, Inc., photographers. Crowds on the hillside in Riverside Park near Grant's Tomb, including police; woman who has fainted or fallen; ships on the river, including the replica of the Halfmoon, rowboats, warships; dock and reviewing stand; police on horseback; officers and officials on the reviewing stand, parade route, police restraining crowd, units in the parade including men dressed as Indians accompanying a float (I. Order of Red-Men), men in sashes, part of Swedish Hundred Men; float representing various upstate counties, float with men in revolutionary era dress, floats: the trial of John Peter Zenger, a small steamboat, early settlers and Indians, explorers in an icy sea, a Revolutionary War camp, History of New York, Dutch settlers, St. Nicholas, a coach and four, eagle with e. Pluribus Unum banner, Indians, women in classical garb, Broadway line [sleigh], the Half Moon soldiers and a fort, firemen and equipment, Colonial Era 1664-1783, George Washington's Inauguration, Jan Smeede's sailing ship, birch bark canoe and Indians, Propery Wagon, men pulling down the statue of George IV, the Clermont, the Stamp Act, a windmill, the Statue of Liberty, Indians at a royal court.
- [Album of images of ships], [1960-1969] (Offsite-box 27, Volume 206)
  Photographs, postcards, exhibition notice, invitation, Christmas cards, and other materials depicting contemporary and historic ships, including snapshots on the deck and bridge of the Britannic of Liverpool; article about Modigliani and ballet laid in; children's drawings laid in.
- Presented to Hon. Randolph Guggenheimer, president of the Council of the City of New York by the National Sculpture Society in recognition of his co-operation in the erection of the triumphal arch and colonnade to the glory of our Navy and in honor of Admiral Dewey, September 30, 1899 (Offsite-box 47, Volume 207)
  Second page lists contributing member of the National Sculpture society, beginning with J.Q.A. Ward. Views depicting the construction of the Dewey Arch from a wax model, the site on Madison Square, men working in modeling studio, scaffolding, carriages and trolleys on the street; various views of completed arch, including one with photographer standing at base, and views of the grandstand and crowds.
- Central Bridge over the Harlem River, New York City, and approaches thereto, [1895] (Offsite-box 27, Volume 208)